Finding Aid for Jeaneane Havstad papers, 1968-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jeaneane Havstad papers 1968-1982, 1972-1976
Havstad, Jeaneane.
3 linear feet
2012057 Aa 2
Jeaneane Havstad was a political activist whose work spanned various cities and counties throughout Michigan. She became the first elected Chairperson of the Human Rights Party of Michigan in 1971. The Jeaneane Havstad Papers reflect her involvement in numerous political activities, chiefly the Human Rights Party.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Jeaneane Havstad (donor no. 10658 ) in November 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jeaneane Havstad spent more than a decade on issue and electoral political activities in various cities and counties throughout Michigan, starting in the late 1960s. Following her grassroots involvement in politics and the Vietnam peace movement, she joined other progressives and members of the New Democratic Coalition of Michigan in splintering off from the more conservative-leaning Michigan Democratic Party to found the Human Rights Party (HRP) of Michigan in late 1970. Havstad became its first elected Chairperson in 1971, with chapters in 10 counties and cities in Michigan. During her tenure, the HRP successfully established its viability in the electoral process by electing members to the Ann Arbor city council on a partisan ballot.
The scope of Havstad’s activities included the coordination of a variety of statewide, local and metro-Detroit area political efforts, especially on behalf of Zolton Ferency, as an HRP candidate for Governor of Michigan, and for the Michigan Supreme Court. She was also part of an earlier successful effort challenging the formula for the election of trustees to Schoolcraft Community College, in Livonia.
The Jeaneane Havstad Papers documents her involvement in numerous political activities, chiefly the Human Rights Party. The collection is arranged into three series: Personal, Politics, and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Havstad, Jeaneane.; Human Rights party (Mich.); New Democratic Coalition of Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1972.; Radicalism--Michigan.; Women--Political activity--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series is divided into four subseries: Red Squad Case Files, Manuscripts, Correspondence, and Photographs. The Manuscripts section contains draft and final writings of Havstad that she submitted for publication. They are primarily concerned with the rise, activity, and fall of the Human Rights Party. The Correspondence section is arranged chronologically by year. Havstad frequently wrote politicians at the local, state and federal level. Sometimes they responded specifically to Havstad's issues, such as a 1972 letter from the office of then-Congressman Gerald R. Ford.
  - Red Squad Case Files
    - Clippings 1980, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Peter Havstad, scattered and undated (Box 1)
    - Jeaneane Havstad, scattered and undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1969-1973 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts 1979, 1980 (Box 1)
- Politics
  The Politics series offers the richest source of materials within the collection. Its arrangement covers four areas: Political Parties, Initiatives, and Campaigns. Havstad partook in advocacy through many organizations, ranging from the Human Rights Party to the People's Party. The People's Party overlapped with some other groups, as records reflect coordination between it and the Human Rights Party. Folders are grouped by the function they served within the respective party. Campaigns are listed by the name of the politician for which Havstad was organizing, therein followed by function and chronology. Records from the campaign of Zolton Ferency span several different elections and offices.
  - Political Parties
    - Human Rights Party
      - History
        - Clippings 1969-1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Beginnings 1969-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Whatever Happened to the Human Rights Party of Michigan?
          - Reference Material 1967-1982 (Box 1)
          - Material Draft 1980 (Box 1)
        - Decline undated (Box 1)
      - Administrative
        - Meeting Minutes 1970-1977 (scattered and undated) (Box 1)
        - Constitutions and Procedures 1972-1974 (Box 1)
        - Legal 1972-1974 (Box 1)
      - Official Communications
        - Meeting Notices 1970-1974 (Box 1)
        - Mailings 1971-1977 (Box 1)
        - Press Releases 1971-1973 (Box 1)
        - Miscellaneous 1972-1973 (Box 1)
        - Newsletters 1972-1976 (scattered) (Box 1)
      - Printed Materials
        - Campaign Flyers 1972 (Box 1)
        - Literature undated (Box 1)
        - Platforms
          - General 1972 (Box 1)
          - National Coalition Platform Committee Recommendations, scattered and undated (Box 1)
        - Positions undated (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous 1972, undated (Box 1)
    - New Democratic Coalition of Michigan
      - Literature 1968-1969, undated (Box 2)
      - Coalition Commentary 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - Communication 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - Minutes 1969, 1970 (Box 2)
      - Publications 1969, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Resolutions 1970, undated (Box 2)
    - People's Party
      - New Party 1969-1971 (Box 2)
      - National Third Party Convention in Albuquerque 1971 (Box 2)
      - Internal Communication 1971-1973 (Box 2)
      - Peace and Freedom Party 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - Candidates 1972 (Box 2)
      - Pamphlets 1972 (Box 2)
      - Publications
        - Grass Roots, 1972-1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Our Newsletter 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Initiatives
    - Antiballistic Missile System 1969 (Box 2)
    - Biafra 1969 (Box 2)
    - Education 1969-1973 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Petitions 1970 (Box 2)
    - Schoolcraft College Trustees Lawsuit 1971 (Box 2)
    - Schoolcraft College Trustees Lawsuit Clippings 1971 (Box 2)
    - American Friends Service Committee 1972 (Box 2)
    - Awareness House "Rap on Parks," 1972, undated (Box 2)
    - Livonia Roads 1973 (Box 2)
    - Livonia Roads Clippings 1973 (Box 2)
    - Detroit City Charter 1974 (Box 2)
    - Public Power 1976 (Box 2)
    - Public Power Clippings 1976 (Box 2)
  - Campaigns
    - Zolton Ferency
      - Candidacy Statement 1972 (Box 3)
      - Clippings 1972-1976 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1972-1976 (scattered) (Box 3)
      - Election Returns 1972 (Box 3)
      - Events 1972 (Box 3)
      - Financial Records 1972-1976 (Box 3)
      - Strategy 1972, 1976 (Box 3)
      - History 1975-1981, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Bills Paid and Received 1976 (Box 3)
      - Campaign Literature 1976, undated (Box 3)
      - Mailing List 1976 (Box 3)
    - Ronald B. Hecker
      - Campaign Resolutions 1969, undated (Box 3)
      - Clippings 1970 (Box 3)
      - Election Returns 1970 (Box 3)
      - General 1970 (Box 3)
      - Press Releases 1970 (Box 3)
    - Ed Pierce
      - Contacts 1976 (Box 3)
      - Election Returns 1976 (Box 3)
      - Literature 1976 (Box 3)
      - Planning 1976 (Box 3)
    - Michael Peacock
      - Clippings 1972 (Box 3)
      - Contacts 1972 (Box 3)
      - Election Returns 1972 (Box 3)
      - Literature 1972 (Box 3)
      - Platforms 1972 (Box 3)
      - Strategy 1972 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files are arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically thereafter. Of particular interest are rare periodicals such as the Ann Arbor Sun, Eagle Eye, and Freedom Reader. A 1972 Havstad editorial to the Livonia Observer regarding depictions of women in beauty pageants generated considerable response from local readers. Included in this folder is a copy of the article along with correspondence to and from responders.
  - Precinct Maps and Zipcode Maps 1968-1975 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Vietnam Moratorium 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Anti-War Platform Adopted by Michigan Democrats 1970 (Box 3)
  - The Eagle Eye, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Freedom Reader, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Ann Arbor Sun 1972 (Box 3)
  - Election Clippings 1972 (Box 3)
  - Editorial to Livonia Observer, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Utility News Clippings, Flyers, and Information 1975-1976 (Box 3)